<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://mdalifaisal.github.io/mdalifaisal/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://mdalifaisal.github.io/mdalifaisal/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2023-12-16T11:20:37+00:00</updated><id>https://mdalifaisal.github.io/mdalifaisal/feed.xml</id><title type="html">M. Ali Faisal</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Can we catch the uncatchable? An attempt to capture Turkish Lira’s hyper volatility!</title><link href="https://mdalifaisal.github.io/mdalifaisal/blog/2023/liravolatility/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can we catch the uncatchable? An attempt to capture Turkish Lira’s hyper volatility!"/><published>2023-04-22T09:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-04-22T09:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mdalifaisal.github.io/mdalifaisal/blog/2023/liravolatility</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mdalifaisal.github.io/mdalifaisal/blog/2023/liravolatility/"><![CDATA[<p>Saying that the Turkish lira experienced high volatility during the last decade would be an understatement. We can see why this is true if we compare a simple variance measure, i.e., the annualized standard deviation of the lira, with other major currencies. From 2011 onwards, the lira’s sd stands at <strong>17.2%</strong> compared to the Australian dollar’s 10.4%, Swiss franc’s 10.3%, Japanese yen’s 9.04%, Euro’s 8.5%, and Canadian dollar’s 7.5%.</p> <div> <iframe width="900" height="800" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" src="//plotly.com/~alishaikh1119/1.embed"></iframe> </div> <p><em>Note:</em> The code used to generate this graph is available at my GitHub <a href="https://github.com/mdalifaisal/blogs/tree/main/lira">repository</a></p> <p>Like many other financial assets, we can analyze the lira’s behavior through chartist’s or fundamentalist’s lenses. While covering such two broad perspectives in this short blog is quite challenging, I will summarize the overall situation via these two schools of thought.<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> Fundamentalists view the expected changes in economic variables to forecast asset prices. As for the exchange rate, probably the most critical variable is the short-term interest rate. Interest rates are a natural choice as a policy instrument to offset the financial uncertainty encompassing the currency. And like other central banks, the Central Bank of the Republic of Turkey (CBRT) used it to control the free fall. Take the one-week repo rate between 2016 and 2018 as an example. It increased from 8% to 16.5% (850 bps) at the beginning of 2018 and eventually reached 24% by September 2018, following a 40% depreciation of the lira in mid-August. However, it got gradually reduced in the subsequent announcements. The lira kept receiving shocks, the worst of which came after the global pandemic. On the 20^{th} of December 2021, the nominal value against USD reached an all-time high of 18.4, decreasing to a closing value of 13.5 the next day. The government announced a scheme on the same day to curb the effects of dollarization. It aimed to protect the lira deposits in the banks against fluctuations in foreign exchange markets. In the past, CBRT also used instruments like reserve option mechanism (ROM), required reserve ratio (RRR), and interest rate corridor (IRO), which were only partially successful. While it goes without saying that the central bank’s policy tools are just a part of the larger picture, noted here is that simply the increase or decrease of the repo rates and reserve requirements won’t control the shocks that may stem from supply and demand or other sources. Domestic and overseas capital movements, geopolitical uncertainty, or even economic uncertainty play their respective roles too. In a recent research (I did as part of my Ph.D. program), some of my results suggested that economic policy uncertainty influenced volatility, especially long-run variance.</p> <p>In the same paper, we modeled the Turkish lira’s volatility with seven different groups of statistical approaches, having 76 specifications. Most of the models used estimated volatility with univariate model classes. This idea brings us to the chartist point of view, which states that an asset’s price movements may have an explanation in its history. Our findings were intriguing from several perspectives. Firstly, we observed that to model the lira’s volatility, model specifications with non-gaussian error distributions; provided comparatively decent results. Secondly, it isn’t always necessary to have over complicated techniques to model a currency like a lira. For example, many simple specifications gave better estimates than fancy models; that had jump components in them. In the final part of our study, we applied a support vector regression (SVR) to our variables. We did so to check the effectiveness of an estimate. We showed that this effect depends highly on the proxy used as a dependent variable. For example, when we use the range return <em>(RR)</em> of Parkinson’s as a proxy, estimates from range-based models were better able to explain the variation. We share a part of our analysis in the bar graphs below to provide a brief idea regarding our findings. We used three proxies as dependent volatility measures; these are <em>RR</em>, realized volatility <em>(RV)</em>, and moving average squared returns <em>(MASR)</em>, given in Figures 1, 2, and 3, respectively.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/mdalifaisal/assets/img/fig1-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/mdalifaisal/assets/img/fig1-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/mdalifaisal/assets/img/fig1-1400.webp"/> <img src="/mdalifaisal/assets/img/fig1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <figcaption align="center"><b>Figure 1 - Models explaining variance</b></figcaption> </div> </div> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/mdalifaisal/assets/img/fig2-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/mdalifaisal/assets/img/fig2-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/mdalifaisal/assets/img/fig2-1400.webp"/> <img src="/mdalifaisal/assets/img/fig2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <figcaption align="center"><b>Figure 2 - Models explaining variance</b></figcaption> </div> </div> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/mdalifaisal/assets/img/fig3-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/mdalifaisal/assets/img/fig3-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/mdalifaisal/assets/img/fig3-1400.webp"/> <img src="/mdalifaisal/assets/img/fig3.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <figcaption align="center"><b>Figure 3 - Models explaining variance</b></figcaption> </div> </div> <p><strong><em>Disclaimer:</em></strong> Some of the points highlighted in this blog are a part of the second chapter of my Ph.D. dissertation and a paper I have co-authored with my supervisor Prof. Dr. Murat Donduran, of Yildiz Technical University. The code and data used in our paper are also available in a GitHub <a href="https://github.com/mdalifaisal/lira_volatility_code">repository</a>.</p> <div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"> <ol> <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote"> <p>In a future blog, I intend to cover the main theoretical and empirical models of the exchange rates and hopefully provide a map that provides a systematic picture of the information derived from the literature. It is such an interesting and important issue; that I feel deserves a separate effort! <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> </ol> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="finance-posts"/><category term="rplot"/><category term="econometrics"/><category term="finance"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[blog on the lira's volatility]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Z-ing in the right direction? A closer look at the European banking system’s stability</title><link href="https://mdalifaisal.github.io/mdalifaisal/blog/2023/zscore/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Z-ing in the right direction? A closer look at the European banking system’s stability"/><published>2023-01-16T18:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-16T18:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mdalifaisal.github.io/mdalifaisal/blog/2023/zscore</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mdalifaisal.github.io/mdalifaisal/blog/2023/zscore/"><![CDATA[<p>If there is one measure that we can trust to give us an overall risk situation of the banking operations, arguably it’d be the z-score. Primarily, it is because its calculation reflects profit and equity rather than just loan book items. In this short blog, we will try to cover the basic premise of the concept at the micro level. Can it give us a larger picture of an economy’s banking system? And finally, what insights can we obtain by observing the z-score of European banks before and after the global pandemic?</p> <p>So let’s dive in!</p> <p>At its core, a z-score predicts the probability of bankruptcy, where a high score generally means fewer chances of being insolvent. Prof. Altman published it in his famous paper in 1968. Since then, z-score has been used extensively not only by academics; but also by practitioners, analysts, and regulators. In his recent paper, Prof. Altman has defined some of the applications given in the table below <sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>:</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/mdalifaisal/assets/img/table1-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/mdalifaisal/assets/img/table1-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/mdalifaisal/assets/img/table1-1400.webp"/> <img src="/mdalifaisal/assets/img/table1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>As far as banks are concerned, we use a slightly modified version of the original z-score.</p> \[Z = \frac{ROA+(LR)}{\sigma(ROA)}\] <p>where \(ROA\) is the return on assets, \(LR\) is the leverage ratio measured as a fraction of equity and assets, and \(\sigma(ROA)\) is the standard deviation of return on assets. Just by looking at the formula, we can develop intuition. A z-score objectively measures the bank’s ability to counter risk by using a ratio of its profits and equity to every unit of volatility. Therefore, the greater the number, the higher is resistance toward risk shocks.</p> <p>Moving on to our next objective, which is to define what z-score could mean at the macro level. At the risk of overgeneralizing, if we take aggregate values of equity, assets, and profits, we can easily end up with a z-score of an industry or in our case, banking systems. What risks do we have in doing so? We might mask the variations present within a country’s banking system. For example, the ratios of small banks may differ from those of big banks in magnitude. That means a higher ratio may be misleading. Since it does not reveal what kind of risks encompass a particular group of banks within an economy. But to obtain a wide perspective and see what aggregation entails, let’s ignore these issues for a moment. This may lead us towards benchmarking for comparison of different states.</p> <p>If we were to take the formula above, we can easily translate its meaning to the macro level. A commercial banking system’s z-score, as per World Bank’s definition, <strong>“captures the probability of default of a country’s banking system. Z-score compares the buffer of a country’s banking system (capitalization and returns) with the volatility of those returns.”</strong></p> <p>Even though it is quite difficult to objectively measure the true impact of the global pandemic on financial institutions, we can safely assume that banks had their work cut out as well. Be it digital payments, bailouts, or facilitation of day-to-day operations. In addition, reduced economic activity and higher credit risk for loans did not make their life easy. If we take the z-score as our parameter, we can observe an interesting fact from the graph below.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/mdalifaisal/assets/img/z-score-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/mdalifaisal/assets/img/z-score-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/mdalifaisal/assets/img/z-score-1400.webp"/> <img src="/mdalifaisal/assets/img/z-score.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <hr/> <p><strong>Note:</strong> Code for the above graph can be found at my Github <a href="https://github.com/mdalifaisal/blogs/tree/main/z-score">repository</a>. Data has been taken from <a href="https://databank.worldbank.org/metadataglossary/global-financial-development/series/GFDD.SI.01#:~:text=Z%2Dscore%20compares%20the%20buffer%20of%20a%20country's%20banking%20system,than%205%20bank%2Dlevel%20observations.">Global Financial Database</a></p> <hr/> <p>Apart from Turkey and Poland, we do not observe any significant fall in the score after the worst crisis our financial markets have seen in the last 100 years. Even in the case of these two countries, the score is still above the benchmark, thus not raising any alarms. We can also observe that economies were able to improve their score. Let us now compare these scores with those of the US and the UK. We can see a similar trend. The US achieved a z-score of 31.1 in 2021 from 30.3 in 2020, whereas the UK had 18.1 in 2021, versus 17.6 in 2020.</p> <p>But how were scores improved even though our financial markets faced a once-in-a-lifetime crisis? We can attribute this to several factors: governments, central banks, and/or decent coordination among financial institutions, supportive regulatory measures, strong capital levels, and good asset quality. Similarly, the decline could be attributed to the lack of these elements.</p> <p>This blog was just an attempt to provide some instincts. For analyzing a commercial banking system, we cannot just rely on an overall z-score. Instead, we have to take it in conjunction with other risk measures and variables such as service structure, digitalization, ease of access, etc. In addition, even though financial markets in most European economies have weathered the storm in terms of navigating the crisis, financial stability needs constant monitoring from all sides.</p> <p>We all know the advantage the EU region has over other economies in terms of having connected markets. But, there is always some risk involved in such systems, as the financial crisis in one country can have ripple effects throughout the region.</p> <p><strong><em>Disclaimer:</em></strong> All views are personal and do not represent those of any institution.</p> <div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"> <ol> <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote"> <p>For the complete details &amp; table please see <a href="https://www.mdpi.com/2227-7072/6/3/70">Altman, 2018</a> <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> </ol> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="finance-posts"/><category term="rplot"/><category term="finance"/><category term="economics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[blog on z-score]]></summary></entry></feed>